The previous heap exploitation videos were about abusing application logic. Basically
以前的堆漏洞视频，是关于破解应用程序逻辑的。
because the program used faulty data from the heap. But this time we exploit the heap
基本原理是因为，程序使用了堆中的错误数据。但这次我们利用堆算法本身。
algorithm itself. In this video I want to explore heap level 3 from exploit-exercises
在这段视频中，向你展示 exploit-exercises ProtoStar 的第三级堆漏洞，
protostar which is about the infamous unlink() macro.
是臭名昭著的 unlink() 宏。
This video is based on the excellent phrack article “Once upon a free()”. As you can
这段视频是基于一篇优秀的短语文章“Once upon a free() ”。
see this article is from 2001. So we are still 15 years behind the times and have not yet
正如你看到的，这篇文章是2001年的。所以，我们仍然落后15年，
caught up with the modern state of exploitation. The heap implementation that we will exploit
还没有赶上了现代的漏洞形态。
changed over the years to prevent this kind of attack. But the current versions are still
堆实现，多年来为了防止这种漏洞攻击而改变。
based on this old algorithm, so it’s important to understand this easy version here.
但目前的版本仍然是基于这个旧算法，所以，当前理解这个简单的版本是很重要的。
So let’s start by looking at the code of this level.
所以，让我们从这个代码开始。
This level introduces the Doug Lea Malloc (dlmalloc) and how heap meta data can be modified
第3级，介绍了dlmalloc，以及如何修改堆元数据，
to change program execution. The goal is obviously to call the function
以更改程序的执行。最终的目标，显然是调用函数winner
winner. First we malloc 3 objects with 32 byte. A.
首先，我们 malloc 3个大小为32字节的对象A，B，C。
B. and C. Then we copy the program arguments to A. B.
然后我们把程序参数复制到A，B，C。
and C. Obviously strcpy is vulnerable because it
显然strcpy是个漏洞，
doesn’t stop us from copying more than 32 byte. So that is our overflow.
因为它不阻止我们，复制超过32字节的内容。这就是我们的溢出。
And then we free again the objects in reverse order, C, B and A.
然后，我们以相反的顺序，再次释放(free)对象，C，B和A。
And we have the printf at the end. So as you can see, there is no obvious application
还有 printf 在最后。所以你可以看到，没有明显的应用逻辑漏洞
logic we could exploit. No use-after-free, no vulnerable pointer on the heap. But still
没有 use-after-free 都懂，堆上，没有漏洞指针。
it’s possible to redirect code execution. And as the description says, this level is
但仍有重定向代码执行的机会。正如描述所说，这个级别是
about corrupting heap meta data. So there is an issue with the heap algorithm, in this
关于损坏堆元数据。因为，这个堆算法有一个问题，
case in the free() function, that we can use to redirect execution to winner().
本例子，就是在free() 函数中，我们可以使用它，将执行重定向到winner() 。
Let’s start by looking at the heap in gdb. To do this let’s add a couple of breakpoints.
让我们先看看 gdb中的堆。为此，我们添加几个断点。
How about at each library function. So break at malloc, strcpy, free and the printf, which
放置在每个库函数上，如何？所以，断点在 malloc，strcpy，free，和printf(虽说，实际上是 puts 函数)。
is actually puts, at the end. Let’s quickly run it, don’t forget the
让我们快速运行吧，
3 arguments and continue until you arrive at the first strcpy. Then check the mapped
别忘了程序的3个参数，继续，到达第一个strcpy。
memory for this process and look for the heap. So this shows us, that our heap area is from
然后检查此进程的映射内存，并查看堆。数据表明，我们的堆区域，
804c to 804d. And we can define a hook-stop to always print like 56 words of this area
从 804c 到了 804d。我们可以定义一个 hook-stop，当我们到达一个断点时，
when we hit a breakpoint. When we now rerun the program we can see how
每次都打印这个区域的56个字。当我们现在重新运行程序时，
the heap develops. Let’s do it. Before we execute the first malloc we don’t
我们可以看到堆是如何扩展开的。好，定义开始。在我们执行第一个 malloc之前，
have a heap yet. After the malloc we can now see the first object on the heap. So remember
我们还没有堆。在malloc之后，我们现在可以看到堆上的第一个对象。
how a heap chunk looks like? This is the size of the current chunk. Which is hex 29. The
所以还记得堆块的样子吗？这是当前块的大小。它是十六进制 29。
last bit indicates if the PREVIOUS chunk is in use. And because it’s the special first
而最后一位，指示前一个块是否正在使用。
chunk, there is no valid memory before that, thus it has the bit set indicating that that
因为这是特殊的，第一区块，在此之前，没有有效的内存，
memory is not avilable, not free. This means the true size of the chunk is hex 28, which
因此它有一个设置位，指示该内存不可用，不空闲。这意味着，块的实际大小其实是 hex 28，
is 40 bytes, so malloc allocated a bit more than 32 bytes. But doesn’t matter to us.
它有40个字节，所以，malloc分配了32个以上的字节。但对我们来说，并不重要。
After this chunk we have the wilderness, which is like the first chunk - a little bit special.
在这一块之后，我们有了荒野(剩余内存)，这就像第一块 —— 但有点特别。
But you can just imagien it as a huge free block still avilable for allocation and that’s
你可以把它想象成一个巨大的，可供分配的空闲区块，
it’s size. And it obviously has the last bit set, because the previous chunk is in
而这就是它的大小。它显然有最后一个设置位，
use. We malloc the second object. Same size. Last bit set because the previous chunk is
因为前一个块是在使用。我们 malloc 了第二个对象。大小相同。最后一个位集，
in use. And the wilderness was updated and has now less free space, but still the previous
因为前一个块是在使用中。荒野被更新了，现在的空闲空间减少了，
chunk is in use. And then the last object. Another one with the same size. Last bit set,
但还是一样，之前的区块正在使用中。那么，最后一个。另一个同样大小的。最后一位集，
because the previous is in use. And less space available in the wilderness.
因为前一个正在使用中。在荒野中，可用空间更少。
Next we execute the string copies. So we copy the first argument which was the As to the
接下来，我们执行字符串复制。所以，我们复制了第一个参数A们，到第一个块，
first chunk. The Bs to the second chunk and the Cs to the third chunk. Obviously we could
B们到第二个块，C们到第三个块。很明显，
have written a lot more and completly overwrite everything. Including the chunk size, which
我们可以写很多且复杂的(字)，来覆盖了所有内容。
is the heap metadata.
包括块大小，这可是堆的元数据。
Next we gonna free them again, so the last chunk got freed. The Cs got overwritten with
接下来，我们要再次释放它们，所以，最后一块被释放了。
zero, because these two words here have special meaning for a free block. So previously we
C们被零覆盖，因为这里的这两个词，对于一个空闲块有特殊的意义。
had allocated blocks. Now we have a block that is available again. Free. Not much else
所以，之前我们有一个分配块。现在，我们的这个区块再次可用。空闲。
changed. Infact those chunks are very small and are considered “fastbins” by malloc.
没什么别的改变。事实上，这些块非常小，被 malloc 认为是“fastbin”。
They behave a little bit different. We will learn about that a little bit later.
他们的行为有点不同。稍后我们会了解这一点。
But let’s continue and free the next one, so we have two free blocks. This time our
但是，让我们继续，并释放下一个，所以我们有两个空闲块。
Bs got overwritten with an address, and it points to the other free block. So that’s
这次是我们的B被一个地址覆盖，它指向一个其他的空闲块。
the special meaning of the overwritten word, they are pointers, pointing to the next free
而这就是覆盖词的特殊含义，它们是指针，
block. A linked list.
指向下一个空闲块。一个链表。
Okay continue and free the next one, and we extend that linked list. The first free block
好的，继续并释放下一个，然后，扩展链表。
points to the second one, and that second one points to the third one, which is the
第一个空闲块指向第二个，第二个指向第三个，
last block before the wilderness. You probably ask yourself why the last bit
即荒野前的最后一个块。你可能会问自己为什么
of the sizes, which indicate that the previous blocks are in-use didn’t get set to 0. It’s
最后一位的大小是这个，明明前一个块使用，却不是 0。
a bit confusing, but think like an algorithm for a second. In this case, they are small
它有点混乱，但仔细想想。在这种情况下，
fast bins and we want to be super fast handling them. And how we freed blocks in this reverse
有个很小，但要快的垃圾箱，我们要超快速地处理它们。以及
order, it just doesn’t matter. It would be unnecessary wasted time to set
要在这个反顺序释放块，这其实没关系的。
that bit. Just imagining this pointer somewhere, which always points to the first free chunk.
不必要浪费时间那个位。想象一下，这个指针在什么地方，它总是指向第一个空闲块。
When I now want to malloc something and look for free space, I can then simply follow the
当我现在想 malloc 某些东西，要找个空闲的地方的时候，
linked list to find all free chunks and thus the information that a previous chunk is free
我就可以简单按照链表，查找所有空闲块，而前一个块是否空闲的信息，
is just irrelevant, right? But, It would also look a little bit different if the chunk sizes
对我来说，都无关紧要，对吧？但是，如果块的大小更大，就会有点不同。
were bigger. Then malloc and free would clean up a little bit more and use more heap metadata
malloc和free之后要清理更多，并使用更多的堆元数据来清除干净。
for housekpeeing. But let’s not get hung up on this. We will walk through some part
但，我们不要总停在这里。
of the algirthm later and clear up some parts.
后面，我们再走过一部分算法，和清理一些部分。
So let’s have a look in the code. When you look for the dlmalloc algorithm for this case,
让我们看看代码。当您为这个案例，寻找dlmalloc算法时，
make sure you have a version that is over 15 years old, otherwise you look at a patched
确保你有一个超过15年的版本，
version.
否则你会看到一个补丁版本。
Now before we start reading the code, think for a moment what we are looking for. We look
现在，在我们开始阅读代码之前，先考虑一下我们在寻找什么。
for a primitive that allows us to perform an arbitrary write. That would allow us to
我们在找哪些，能允许我们执行任意写入的标语。
overwrite an entry in the global offset table. One possible way how such code that can be
这样我们就可以，覆盖GOT中的条目。
abused for that looks like, is following pointers that we control, right? If there is some kind
一种可能方法说，有漏洞的代码的样子，就是跟踪我们控制的指针，对吗？
of code here that performs a write based on pointers on the heap we can overflow, we win.
如果这里的代码，可以基于溢出堆上的指针，来执行写操作，我们就赢了。
Let’s keep that in mind when we look at the code.
查看代码时，请记住这一点。
The function starts with the parameter mem, which is the address we want to free. Shortly
函数，以参数 mem 开始，这是我们想要释放的地址。
afterwards mem2chunk is called which get the address two words ahead of mem, which is the
不久后，mem2chunk 被调用，它在 mem 前面，得到两个字地址，
true starting address of the chunk. The first if we reach contains only a little
就是 块的实际起始地址。我们到达的第一个，
bit of code. And it refers to fastbins. THis is exactly what we witnessed when we freed
只有一点点代码。快速垃圾箱的代码。当我们让32字节小块空闲时，
our small 32byte chunks. It updated the first pointer, the fd pointer. Which created the
正是我们期待的。它更新了第一个指针 fd指针，
linked list. But otherwise not much happens and thus it’s not interesting.
会创建这个链表。但除此之外，不会发生太多事情，因此也不有趣。
So this means we just really want to make sure, that our size is greater than the maximum
这意味着，我们只是想确定，我们的尺寸大于Fastbin块大小的最大值，定义为80。
fastbin chunk size, which is defined as 80. Our chunk sizes are 32, so we wanna make sure
我们的块大小是32，
that we overflow the size of the chunk we handle.
所以我们要确保，我们溢出，处理块的大小。
If we head into the else if, we arrive at an interesting comment:
如果，我们进到这个“else if”，我们会得到一个有趣的注释：
“Consolidate other non-mmaped chunks”. If we check what is necessary to pass this
“合并，其他非映射块”。如果我们检查通过这个测试的必要条件
test, we look at the chunk_is_mmaped macro which takes the size of p, which is the size
这 chunk_is_mmaped 一个简单的宏，拿着 p 的 大小，就是当前块的大小，
of the current chunk, and checks the IS_MMAPPPED flag. Very similar to the PREV_INUSE bit,
并检查 IS_MMAPPPED 标志。非常类似于 PREV_INUSE 位，就是最后一，
which is the last one, the IS_MMAPPED flag is the second last bit. So when we want to
IS_MMAPPED 标志是最后第二位。所以，当我们想要到达这里的代码，
reach the code in here, we have to make sure that the 2nd last bit is not set.
我们必须确保没有设置最后第二位。
Then we get the address of the next chunk, which we can calculate based on the size of
然后，我们得到下一个块的地址，我们可以基于当前块的大小计算而来。
our current chunk. So with an overflow, the size is already something we can control,
因此，如果出现一个溢出，那么，大小就是我们已经可以控制的了，
this means, that here we have a first opportunity to fool free() into thinking some other data
这意味着，在这里我们有了第一次机会，
is the next chunk. After that we have a check if the previous
愚弄 free() 把其他数据是下一块。在那之后，我们要检查一下，前一个块是否在使用中，
chunk is in use, if the previous chunk would not be in use, which is defined by the lowest
如果前一块不是在使用中，则由最低设置位定义为 0，
bit set to 0, we would follow the prev_size, which we haven’t introduced yet, but it’s
我们将遵循 prev_size，我们还没有介绍，
this word before our chunk size. And thus calculates the address of the previous chunk.
但它时在我们的块大小之前的词，从而计算前一块的地址。
Again, a value we possibly can control. Then we execute an unlink. That’s the magic
同样，一个我们可以控制的值。然后，我们执行一个 unlink。
word I mentioned at the beginning. So let’s see what that means.
这就是，我在开头提到的魔法咒语。让我们看看这意味着什么。
The first parameter p, is the block before our current block, which we got by following
第一个参数 p，是在当前块之前的块，我们通过 prev_size 方法得到 。
the prev_size. We take the forward and backward pointer of that chunk, which is the first
我们取得，块的前后指针，
and second word after the size and remember it in FD and BK.
这是在大小之后的第一个和第二个词，在fd 和 bk中，记住它。
For simplicity ignore the -&gt;bk and -&gt;fd, because that just references a small offset from the
为了简单起见，忽略 -&gt; bk和 -&gt; fd，因为它这个地址引用的小偏移距离。
address here. We add those offsets afterwards. So now we write the address BK, to the address
我们在后面，加上这些偏移量。所以现在我们把地址bk，写到fd指向的地址
where FD is pointing to. And then we write FD to the address where
然后，我们把FD 写到BK指向的地址。
BK is pointing to. Or to be exact at their respective offsets
或者精确到各自的偏移量，
where the prev and next pointer is stored.
这是存储前一个和下一个指针的位置。
Okay stop! BK could be the address of the winner function. And FD+12 could be our GoT
好了，停！bk 可以是 winner函数的地址。fd+12可能是我们GOT中，puts()的条目。
table entry for puts(). This would overwrite an entry in the global
这用Winner函数去覆盖条目。
offset table with the winner function. This sounds perfect!!!
这听起来很完美！！！！
But we forget the next part, where we would take our GOT address in FD and attempt to
但是，我们忘记了下一部分，我们将在fd中，获取我们的got地址，
write it to the address of Winner (+8). Mhhh… that would segfault. We can’t write
并尝试把它写在 winner 地址（+8 偏移）。嗯… 会有个分段错误了。
into the code segment. Damnit… But now you just have to get creative. Think
我们不能写入这个代码段。该死的… 但现在你必须要有创造力。思考它。
about. If we have two memory segments. Segment A and B. We can write an address from segment
如果，我们有两个内存段。段A和段B。我们可以把地址从，段A写入段B
A into segment B. And we write an address from segment B into segment A. The global
和我们把B段的地址，写进A段。
offset table is writeable, so that could be one of those segments, just the code segment
GOT是可写的，因此它可能是这些段中的一个，
can’t be the other one. But the HEAP could be our second one. We can write to the heap.
只是代码段不能是另一个。但堆可以是我们的第二堆。我们可以写入堆。
This would allow us to write an address from the Heap to the global offset table, and some
这将允许我们将地址，从堆写入GOT，以及
unimportant address from the global offset table will be written into the heap! This
全局偏移表中不重要的地址,将写入堆中！
means we can redirect code execution via the global offset table to shellcode that we can
意味着，我们可以通过GOT，将代码执行重定向到，
place on the Heap. and then this shellcode calls winner for us.
我们放在堆里的 shellcode。然后，这个shellcode为我们调用winner。
That sounds like an awesome plan. Let’s take the state of the heap as we know
听起来是个很棒的计划。拿上我们知道的堆状态，
it and think about how we would want to construct the case we just explained.
想想我们会如何构建我们刚刚解释的案例。
So we could decide that we want to free the last block and make sure the prev in_use bit
因此，我们可以决定释放最后一个块，并确保前一个 in_use 位设置为0。
set to 0. So that it attempts to consolidate the previous block. Let’s actually make
以便它尝试合并前一个块。让我们用 gdb，让这些改变落实，
those changes right here with gdb, this way we can directly test it. Set the chunk size
这样我们就可以直接测试它了。
to more than 80 and have the prev in use bit set to 0. So why not 100. Now we want to set
设置块大小大于80，并将前一个 in_use 位设置为0。为什么不100呢？
the prev_size, to point to the previous block we want to merge with. Let’s make that a
现在，我们要设置 prev_size，指向要合并的前一个块。
small block. So maybe hex 10.
让我们做一个小块。也许是十六进制10。
This means at -0x10 we have to create a fake chunk. Of that size. So set 0x11, because
这意味着，在-0x10 我们必须创建一个假块。至于大小。就设置 0x11，
we want to indicate that the chunk before this fake chunk would be in use. great.
因为我们，想指出在这个假块之前的块是在用的。都挺好。
Now we need the address from puts in the global offset table. This will be the forward pointer
现在我们需要在全局偏移表中 puts 的地址。这将是向前的指针，
where the 2nd pointer will be written to at +12. That’s why you have to do puts-12,
这里第二个指针会在 +12 写入。这就是为什么你必须是 puts-12，
because it will be written to the address +12. And the other pointer will be the address
因为它将被写入 地址 +12。另一个指针，是我们写入GOT的地址
that we write to the global offset table, so that one should point somewhere into the
这样，就应该指向堆的某个地方，
heap where we can place some shellcode. Why not go here.
在那里，我们可以放置一些shellcode。为什么不到了呢？
Just one other thing to consider, before we can test it, the size is used to calculate
在我们测试它之前，只需要考虑另外一件事，
the next chunk and the next size. And after the unlink those values are used. So if we
大小用于计算下一块和下一个大小。在 unlink 后，这些值会使用到。
use the size 100, we point into some unused memory and we have to make sure that the values
所以如果我们使用100大小，我们会指向一些未使用的内存，
there behave nicely. Otherwise we will crash somewehere. There is an if-check if the next
这样我们必须确保这些内存是好的。否则我们会撞车的。
chunk is the top, or what we call wilderness. But our size is overshooting that address.
这有个if 检查，关于下一块是顶部，或是荒野。若是我们的规模，超过了那个地址。
This means we land in this if-case. And now it calculates the next block of that one and
这意味着，我们进入了这种情况。现在它计算下一个块，
checks the prev in use bit to figure out if the block before it is free or not. So if
检查 prev-in-use 位，以确定之前的块，是否空闲。
it is not in use we perform another unlink to also merge the unused block after the current
所以如果它不在使用中，我们执行另一个 unlink ，以便在当前块之后，合并未使用的块。
one. Which copies around those pointers.
在这些指针周围复制。
Hey, this is LiveOverflow from the future. I’m just editing this part and I realized
嘿，这是来自未来的我。我只是在编辑这部分，
that I missread the code here. I thought I had the choice between this short unlink if
我意识到，我误读了这里的代码。我想我可以在这段短时间内，
case, or the whole else case below. But I missed that there are no curly braces, which
选择 短的 unlink if 案例，或者下面的整个案例。但我看错了，这是没有花括号，
means the else case is just this clear_inuse_bit_at_offset. When I was developing this proof of concept
也就是说，else 情况就是 clear_inuse_bit_at_offset。当我开发这个概念证明的时候，
I thought to myself I don’t want to overcomplicate it with the code down here. Infact I made
我对自己说，我不想用下面的代码，过度复杂化它。
it over complicated because we have to construct another fake chunk now to deal with this second
事实上我做的太复杂了，因为我们现在必须构建另一个假块，
unlink in here. But whatever, I think that was a great learning experience. Let’s head
来处理在这里第二个 unlink 。但不管怎样，我认为这是一次很好的学习经历。
back into the episode.
让我们回到这一集。
At this point we should have already succeeded in writing our heap address to the global
此时，我们应该已经成功地用 前一个 unlink，
offset table with the previous unlink, so we can just pick two random heap values to
把堆地址写入GOT，因此我们可以只选取两个随机堆值，
not crash here.
放在这里没有损坏的。
So those are two more fake chunks. With the forward and backward pointer pointing into
所以，这是另外两个假块。
the heap which we don’t care about.
向前和向后指针指向我们不关心的那堆。
This is LiveOverflow from the future. Again. I just realized I made another small mistake
这是未来的LiveOverflow。再一次。我刚刚意识到，我又犯了一个小错误
which negates my false assumption about the big else case from earlier.
这否定了，我之前对大 else 的错误假设。
I actually did set the prev_in_use bit, which means it does NOT consolidate this fake chunk.
我确实设置了prev-in-use位，这意味着，它不会合并这个假块。
Not to mention that I set the fd and bk pointer for the wrong chunk anyway. Should have been
更不用说，我为错误的块，设置了fd和bk指针。
on the other chunk before. I’m sorry guys. I’m just a noob.
应该是在之前那另一块上。对不起，伙计们。我只是个笨蛋。
So to summarize. We change the size of the block we are going to free. We create a fake
总结一下。我们改变，我们将要释放的块的大小。
free chunk before our current one to trigger an unlink and overwrite the GoT. And we created
我们创造了一个假释放块，在当前块触发 unlink 之前，用来覆盖got。
two fake chunk afterwards, where the second one says about the previous that it is in
之后，我们创造了两个假块，
use. Thus not triggering another unlink. And those two values here were unecessary.
第二块写的是，前一块在使用。因此不会触发另一个 unlink 。这两个值是不必要的。
Now if we continue and execute the first free, we can check the entry for puts and we see
现在，如果我们继续执行第一个 gree，我们可以检查，puts的条目，
the function address was sucsessfully written. And when we look at the heap, we can see that
然后我们看到函数地址已成功写入。当我们看到堆的时候，
at the offset +8 we have a GOT address written. Awesome. And when we continue to the puts
我们可以看到在偏移量+8处，我们有一个写入GOT的地址。雕。
and single step forward we jump into the heap. AWESOME!
当我们继续 puts 和 步进，我们跳进了堆。雕！
This works! Now we just have to get these values into the heap with the strcpy…
这是有效的！现在我们，只需要用strcpy，将这些值放入堆中…
Oh no. oh nonononono. I’m stupid. Strcpy can’t copy nullbytes. A string in C is defined
哦，不，不，不。我很笨。strcpy 无法复制 nullbytes。
to end with NULL. So we can’t write sizes like hex 10 into memory. At least not multiple
C定义的字符串，是以 null 结尾。所以，我们不能把十六进制10这样的大小，写进内存。
times. Oh dammit. The whole plan doesn’t work in this case… if it were a read() it
至少不是多数。哦，该死的。在这种情况下，整个计划都不起作用…
would work. But not with strcpy.
如果它是 read()的话 会起作用。但用的是 strcpy。
I go sit in my corner now and think about all the failures in life. See you soon. Maybe.
我现在坐在角落里，想着生活中的所有失败。期待很快与您见面。也许吧。